Guide to the Kurt Wolff Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Kurt Wolff archive
1907-1938
YCGL MSS 3
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.38
(11 boxes)
The papers consist of letters, manuscripts, and other documents from the business files of Kurt Wolff Verlag. Chiefly correspondence with authors of the German Expressionist literary movement. Includes contracts, financial statements, and documentary material. Correspondents include Walter Hasenclever, Franz Kafka, and Franz Werfel. Most letters to the Kurt Wolff Verlag are directed to Kurt Wolff himself; others are addressed to persons associated with the Kurt Wolff Verlag, e.g. Georg Heinrich Meyer, Giovanni Mardersteig, Ernst Rowohlt, Kurt Pinthus, Erik Ernst Schwabach, Lothar Mohrenwitz, René Schickele, Annemarie v. Puttkamer, Arthur Seiffhart, and Daniel Brody. Letters from 1907 to 1912 are directed to the Ernst Rowohlt Verlag (which became the Kurt Wolff Verlag on Feb. 15, 1913). Many letters to the Hyperion Verlag and to the Verlag der Weissen Blätter, some to Der neue Geist Verlag, Genius Verlag, and Verlag der Schriften von Karl Kraus, which all were part of the Kurt Wolff Verlag at one time.
Wolff, Kurt, 1887-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Kurt Wolff, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is also available on microfilm. See Appendix for details.
KURT WOLFF (1887-1963)
In writing about Kurt Wolff shortly after the purchase of his early papers in 1947, Curt von Faber du Faur, curator of the Yale Collection of German Literature, had this to say about his old friend:
"Not every literary generation enjoys the privilege and the benefits of being fostered by an ideal type of publisher, who in one person combines great business acumen with broad scholarship and the requisite love of the fine arts; who carries in his heart a great spiritual tradition which enhances his judgment and sharpens his skills to detect the true values in the present and preserve them for the future. In the Germany of recent years this ideal was personified by Kurt Wolff. During the second and third decades of the present century he gathered about himself virtually all the leading spirits of the younger generation of authors. Most of the outstanding names of this period passed through the portals of his publishing house to recognition and fame; or at least felt themselves honored to have gained the renown of his imprint for one or more of their works. There was scarcely an author who failed to correspond with this keen-visioned publisher who so soon gained for himself the reputation of a tried and true sponsor to his literary friends. It is for this reason that the literary archives of the firm Kurt Wolff, recently acquired by the Library, contain in fact the epistolatory heritage of the spiritual center of the Germany of that period."
(YULG 23:1, 1948, 25)
Kurt Wolff was born in 1887 in Bonn, into a musical household where Brahms was a frequent guest. His first activities as a publisher date from around 1909, when he was studying German literature at Leipzig. There he joined Ernst Rowohlt's fledgling publishing firm, which had been founded the year before. Office space was rented from the Offizin W. Drugulin, well-known for its bibliophile productions. A close relation quickly sprang up between the two firms; the Drugulin Drucke series was in fact overseen by Kurt Wolff.
Rowohlt left the firm in 1912; he joined the S. Fischer Verlag and subsequently established his own publishing house after World War I. In 1913 Wolff changed the name of the old Rowohlt Verlag, of which he was now sole proprietor, to the Kurt Wolff Verlag. When Wolff was called up for military service during the war, the operation was capably run by Georg Heinrich Meyer, many of whose letters will be found among the Yale papers. Wolff returned in 1916.
These early years of the Kurt Wolff Verlag were marked by rapid expansion, undoubtedly due to Wolff's ability to seek out and attract interesting authors and Meyer's genius for advertising. There were highly successful series, such as Der jüngste Tag, 86 volumes of which appeared between 1913 and 1921. A close connection was established with the Verlag der weissen Bücher, which published the influential literary periodical Die weissen Blätter. In 1917, both the Verlag der weissen Bücher and the Hyperion Verlag were acquired by Wolff. A survey of the author list in this register will demonstrate the truth of Faber's statement, cited above, that Wolff was able during these years to gather to himself the leading spirits of the day. There were Expressionists (Benn, Heym, Toller, Trakl), Dadaists (Ball, Hülsenbeck, Tzara), and, presaging Kurt Wolff's interest in art publishing, a number of artists (Gauguin, Grosz, Klee, Kokoschka, Kollwitz, Kubin, Masereel). Correspondence with numerous prominent literary figures is to be found in Kurt Wolff's files: Gerhart Hauptmann, Hesse, Kafka, Karl Kraus, Else Lasker-Schüler, Heinrich and Thomas Mann, Rilke, Werfel, and Wedekind, to name just a few. Nor is the list strictly German, for the collection contains letters by such writers as Gorky, James Joyce, Rabindranath Tagore, and H. G. Wells.
After the war, Kurt Wolff turned more and more toward publishing collected editions rather than new works, toward art publishing, and to the pursuit of his bibliophile interests. In 1920 a close connection with the Ernst Ludwig Presse in Darmstadt was established, and in 1924 Kurt Wolff founded the Pantheon Casa Editrice in Florence, with Hans Mardersteig of the Officina Bodoni as guiding light to the new enterprise.
In 1930, in the wake of personal stress (overwork and divorce) and business difficulties, Kurt Wolff withdrew from publishing. Between 1933 and 1935 he lived in Nice, where a son, Christian, was born to him and his second wife, Helen Mosel. In 1935 the family acquired a farm outside Florence, where they began an experiment in self-sufficiency. In 1939 they moved to Paris. Although the ensuing political events split the family temporarily (Kurt Wolff was incarcerated briefly, the child was sent to the safety of a convent school at La Rochelle), they managed to reunite themselves, escape across the Spanish border, and immigrate to the United States in 1940.
One of Kurt Wolff's principal advisors and supporters in the United States was the curator of Yale's German Literature Collection, Curt von Faber du Faur. Faber offered Kurt Wolff $7,500 as a kind of matching grant: Wolff was to raise an equal amount in order to establish himself anew in business. This he did: Pantheon Books was founded in 1942, at first on the proverbial shoestring but soon attaining a large measure of success. Kurt Wolff had the good fortune to meet Paul Mellon, for whom he published the well-known Bollingen Series. Best-sellers followed: Anne Morrow Lindbergh's Gift from the Sea and the American edition of Pasternak's Doctor Zhivago (1958), for instance. Books like Broch's The Death of Virgil (1945), while undoubtedly not financial successes, showed Wolff's continuing dedication to what he deemed to be worthwhile and timely literature.
In 1959 Helen and Kurt Wolff moved to Locarno. By 1961, however, it proved too difficult to manage the firm from abroad, and they resigned from Pantheon Books, which was acquired by Random House. William Jovanovitch subsequently proposed to the Wolffs that they should oversee a special imprint within Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovitch. The proposal was accepted, but not long after the launching of Helen and Kurt Wolff Books, Kurt Wolff was tragically run down and killed by a truck during a visit to Germany in 1963. Helen Wolff continued with Harcourt, Brace, and Jovanovitch until her retirement, overseeing Helen and Kurt Wolff Books until her death in 1994.
Scope and Contents
The Kurt Wolff papers at Yale consist of about 4,100 letters, telegrams, postcards, documents, and manuscripts from the business files of the Kurt Wolff Verlag, mostly from the period 1910-30. There is no material relating to Kurt Wolff's career as a publisher in the United States. Incoming correspondence from authors is interfiled with copies of letters and other communications by Kurt Wolff and members of the Verlag. Some author files also contain contracts, financial statements, and manuscripts.
The largest single correspondence is that between Franz Werfel and the Verlag, which numbers over 900 items including poetry manuscripts and letters by Werfel's wife Alma Mahler Werfel. There are 605 items of correspondence with Walter Hasenclever, a close friend of Wolff from his Leipzig student days. The letters from Franz Kafka (47 items, 1912-20) constitute one of the high points of the collection.
Most of the letters in the collection are directed to Kurt Wolff himself, but some are addressed to persons associated with the Kurt Wolff Verlag, including Georg Heinrich Meyer, Hans Mardersteig, Ernst Rowohlt, Kurt Pinthus, Erik Ernst Schwabach, Lothar Mohrenwitz, René Schickele, Annemarie von Puttkamer, Arthur Seiffhart, and Daniel Brody. Letters written between 1907 and 1912 are addressed to the Ernst Rowohlt Verlag. Some letters are directed to the Hyperion Verlag, the Verlag der weissen Bücher, Der neue Geist Verlag, Genius Verlag, and the Verlag der Schriften von Karl Kraus, all of which were part of the Kurt Wolff Verlag at some time.
Many of the letters written in German script are provided with typed transcriptions that were made by Yale graduate students under the supervision of Hedwig S. Dejon, librarian of the Yale Collection of German Literature. Soon after its acquisition, the Kurt Wolff Archive was catalogued on cards, with main entries for each of the authors with whom the Kurt Wolff Verlag corresponded. These cards give more detailed information about the material than the following list. They have been retained by the curator of the collection.
Many, although by no means all of the letters in the Yale Kurt Wolff Archive were published by Bernhard Zeller and Ellen Otten in Kurt Wolff. Briefwechsel eines Verlegers. 1911-1963 (Frankfurt: Heinrich Scheffler, 1966). The photocopies used to compile this volume are still on deposit at the Deutsches Literaturarchiv in Marbach, West Germany, where they can be made available to scholars who apply for Yale's permission to examine the material.
Related material will be found in the Helen Wolff papers (Uncat Zg Ms 12), which documents the American phase of Mrs. Wolff's career but also contains some earlier materials.
Appendix A: Guide to the Microfilm
Ms Vault Film 2208 1 1-2 1-47
Ms Vault Film 2176 2 2 48-75
MS Vault Film 2295 3 3-4 76-112
MS Vault Film 2314 4 4-5 113-161
MS Vault Film 2341 5 5-6 162-212
MS Vault film 2296 6 6-7 213-274
MS Vault Film 2297 7 7-8 275-332
MS Vault Film 2298 8 8-9 333-370
MS Vault Film 2342 9 9-10 371-419
MS Vault Film 2325 10 Finding aid
Authors and publishers -- Germany; Authors, German -- Archives; Dadaism; Expressionism; Publishers and publishing -- Germany; Ball, Hugo, 1886-1927; Becher, Johannes Robert, 1891-1958; Benn, Gottfried, 1886-1956; Blei, Franz, 1871-1942; Borchardt, Rudolf, 1877-1945; Brod, Max, 1884-1968; Brody, Daniel, 1883-1969; Dauthendey, Max, 1867-1918; Edschmid, Kasimir, 1890-1966; Eulenberg, Herbert, 1876-1949; Gauguin, Pola, 1883-1961; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936; Grosz, George, 1893-1959; Gundolf, Friedrich, 1880-1931; Hasenclever, Walter, 1890-1940; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; Heym, Georg, 1887-1912; Huelsenbeck, Richard, 1892-1974; Joyce, James, 1882-1941; Kafka, Franz, 1883-1924; Kirchner, Ernst Ludwig, 1880-1938; Klee, Paul, 1879-1940; Kolb, Annette, 1870-1967; Kollwitz, Käthe, 1867-1945; Kraus, Karl, 1874-1936; Kubin, Alfred, 1877-1959; Landauer, Gustav, 1870-1919; Lasker-Schüler, Else, 1869-1945; Lichnowsky, Mechtilde, 1879-1958; Mahler, Alma, 1879-1964; Mann, Heinrich, 1871-1950; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; Mardersteig, Giovanni, 1892-1977; Masereel, Frans, 1889-1972; Meidner, Ludwig, 1884-1966; Meyer, Georg Heinrich; Meyrink, Gustav, 1868-1932; Mohrenwitz, Lothar; Mühsam, Erich, 1878-1934; Pinthus, Kurt, 1886-1975; Puttkamer, Annemarie v.; Rilke, Rainer Maria, 1875-1926; Rolland, Romain, 1866-1944; Rowohlt, Ernst, 1887-1960; Scheerbart, Paul, 1863-1915; Schickele, René, 1883-1940; Schwabach, Erik Ernst; Seiffhart, Arthur; Sternhelm, Carl, 1878-1942; Tagore, Rabindranath, 1861-1941; Toller, Ernst, 1893-1939; Trakl, Georg, 1887-1914; Tzara, Tristan, 1896-1963; Unruh, Fritz von, 1885-1970; Walser, Robert, 1878-1956; Wassermann, Jakob, 1873-1934; Wedekind, Frank, 1864-1918; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946; Werfel, Franz, 1890-1945; Wolfskehl, Karl, 1869-1948; Zech, Paul, 1881-1946; Zuckmayer, Carl, 1896-1977; Zweig, Arnold, 1887-1968; Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942; Kurt Wolff Verlag
- Box and Folder List
  Scope and Contents
  This archive consists of letters to and from Kurt Wolff, among which literary writings of some correspondents have been interfiled. The correspondence has been alphabetically arranged and all letters have been placed in chronological order within each folder.
  - Albert, Eugen d' [with transcript], 1922 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amann, Paul [with transcript], 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andersen Nexo, Martin, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Andreas-Salomé, Lou, 1917-19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asenijeff, Elsa [with transcript], 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bahr, Hermann, 1916-22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bahr-Mildenburg, Anna, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Balázs, Béla, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ball, Hugo [with transcripts], 1911-15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Becher, Johannes Robert [with transcripts], 1914-22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Becker-Glauch, K., 1917-23 (Box 1, Folder 9a-b)
  - Beeh, René [with transcripts], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benn, Gottfried [with transcripts], 1916-17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berger, Ludwig [with transcripts], 1920-22 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Binding, Rudolf Georg [with transcripts], 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Björnsen, Björn, 1920-30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blass, Ernst [with transcripts], 1915-17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Blei, Franz, 1913-21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bloch, Ernst, 1921 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bô Yin Râ: letter [with transcript]; document, 1920 Jul 9 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
  - Boehn, Max von [with transcripts], 1919-20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bötticher, Hans (Ringelnatz, pseud.), 1921-23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bonsels, Waldemar [with transcripts], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Borchardt, Rudolf
    - Correspondence, 1916-18 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - "(Toskanische) Villen" [with fragments], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - "Giovanni Pascoli", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Tagebuchblatt," "Versuch über Heine," "Zum Tode Carduccis," "Über Hofmannsthals Erzählung": latter with typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brod, Max
    - Correspondence [with transcripts], 1914-18 (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
    - Financial papers, 1912-18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Brust, Alfred, 1920-23 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Buber, Martin [with transcript], 1913-14 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Carossa, Hans, ms. Fahrt (poem), 1929 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Caspar, Karl [with transcripts], 1917 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Coudenhove-Kalergi, Richard Nicolaus, Graf von, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dacqué, Edgar, 1925-29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Däubler, Theodor [with transcripts], 1916-20 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dauthendey, Max
    - Correspondence, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Der Venusinenreim, [1911] (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
  - Dehmel, Richard [with transcript], 1919 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dirsztay, Viktor Baron von [with transcripts], 1916-23 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Döblin, Alfred [with transcripts], 1913-21 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Edschmid, Kasimir, 1913-17 (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
  - Ehrenstein, Albert, 1910-23, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Einstein, Carl, [1910]-23 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Essig, Hermann, 1916-21 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Eulenberg, Herbert
    - Correspondence, includes contract, 1913-29 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
    - Alles um Geld
      - Notebook, [1912?] (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Printed version with corrections, 1911-12 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Deutsche Sonette: printed copy, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Drei Einakter: printed copy, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Die Geschwister": typescript, [1912] (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Moderner Prolog": manuscript, [1912] (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Münchhausen
      - Printed copy with corrections, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Corrections, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Ritter Blaubart: printed copy, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - [23] "Sonette": manuscript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Two poems: "Tizian" and "Zur geplanten Gesamtausgabe": manuscript (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Die Welt will betrogen werden: typescript, [1912] (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Die Wunderkur: typescript, [1912] (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Zeitwende: manuscript, ca. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
  - Flake, Otto, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Förster-Nietzsche, Elisabeth [with transcript], 1920 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 71a)
  - Fontana, Oskar Maurus, 1918-21 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Forschungsinstitut für Kulturmorphologie, München, 1922-23 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Frank, Bruno, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Frank, Leonhard [with transcript], 1912-17 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Freeman, John, 1918-19 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Frey, Alexander Moritz [with transcripts], 1921-23 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Friedländer, Max J., 1920-22 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Friedländer, Salomo (pseud. Mynona), 1917-22 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Fuchs, Rudolf
    - Correspondence, 1914-22 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Poem: "Letzter Spruch," Translations: "Magische Mitternacht," "Sommersonnenwende," Untitled (poems by Ottokar Brezina) (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Gauguin, Paul: Avant et Après, typescript, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Gauguin, Pola [with contract], 1913-21 (Box 3, Folder 83-84)
  - Gerlach, Helmut von, 1918-20 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Germain, André, 1920-27 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Godwin, Catherina: "Frau im Kreise," sketch for advertisement [?], 1919-22; n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Goetz, Wolfgang, 1920-23 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Goll, Iwan [with transcript], 1913 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Gor'kii, Maksim, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Gorsleben, Rudolf John, 1912-13 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Grautoff, Otto [with transcripts], 1910 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Grosz, George [with transcripts], 1920-21 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Gulbransson, Grete and Olaf, 1912, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Gundolf, Friedrich, 1907-30 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Hardekopf, Ferdinand, includes contract, 1921-23 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Harden, Maximilian, 1909-17 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Hasenclever, Walter
    - Correspondence [with transcripts], 1911-17 (Box 3, Folder 98-109)
    - Correspondence [with transcripts], 1918-34 (Box 4, Folder 110-30)
    - Writings [with transcript], 1911-13, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Papers, 1916-32, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132-33)
  - Hauptmann, Carl
    - Correspondence, 1911-14 (Box 4, Folder 134-35)
    - Poetry:"Zum Rübezahlbuche," "Zu Kriegsszenen", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Review: "An Carl Hauptmann nach Lektüre seines 'Krieg' von Max Grube", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Hauptmann, Gerhart [with some transcripts], 1921-27 (Box 4, Folder 137-38)
  - Heine, Thomas Theodor, 1920, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Hellpach, Willy [with transcript], 1927 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Henschke, Alfred (Klabund, pseud.) [with transcripts], 1916-18 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Hermann-Neisse, Max [with transcripts], 1917 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Herzog, Wilhelm, 1917 Jan 9 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Hesse, Hermann, 1916-34 (Box 4, Folder 144-45)
  - Heym, Georg
    - Correspondence [with transcripts], 1910-12 (Box 4, Folder 146-49)
    - Guttman correspondence, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Hiller correspondence, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Heym, Hermann (father) correspondence [with transcripts], 1912 (Box 5, Folder 152-53)
  - Heynicke, Kurt [with transcript], 1920 Jul 7 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Hiller, Kurt, 1917-18 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Hofmannsthal, Hugo von [with transcripts], 1918 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Hollander-Lossow, Else v., 1919-20 (Box 5, Folder 156a)
  - Huch, Ricarda [with transcripts], 1921-22 (Box 5, Folder 157)
  - Hülsenbeck, Richard, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Jacobsohn, Siegfried, 1912-18 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Jaloux, Edmond, 1926-27, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Janowitz, Franz, 1914-21 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - Joyce, James [with transcripts], 1920 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - Kafka, Franz, 1912-23 (Box 5, Folder 163-65b)
  - Kainer, Ludwig, 1914-18 (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Kaiser, Georg, 1918 Aug 2 (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - Kerr, Alfred, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 168-69)
  - Keyserling, Hermann, 1922 Nov (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Kirchner, Ernst Ludwig
    - Correspondence, 1920-23 (Box 5, Folder 171-74)
    - Papers, 1920, 1923, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Klee, Paul, 1919-20 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Klein, Stefan J., 1920, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Kölwel, Gottfried [with transcripts], 1914-19 (Box 5, Folder 178)
    includes: "Das weisse Bild" and "Vor dem Schneefall" n.d.
  - Kokoschka, Bohuslav, 1918-19 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Kokoschka, Oskar [with transcripts], 1917 (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - Kolb, Annette, 1913-23 (Box 5, Folder 181-84)
  - Kolbe, Georg, 1920-22 (Box 5, Folder 185)
  - Kollwitz, Käthe, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Kraft, Paul, 1915, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 187)
  - Kraus, Karl
    - Correspondence, 1917-21 (Box 5, Folder 188-90)
    - Papers; undated correspondence, [1917?]-21, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 191)
  - Krell, Max, 1916, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 192)
  - Kubin, Alfred [with transcripts], 1918-21 (Box 5, Folder 193-94)
  - Landauer, Gustav, 1915-19 (Box 5, Folder 195-96)
  - Lasker-Schüler, Else, 1911-16 (Box 5, Folder 197-99)
  - Lautensack, Heinrich [with transcripts], 1910-13 (Box 6, Folder 200)
  - Leonhard, Rudolf [with transcripts], 1915-23 (Box 6, Folder 201-02)
  - Lichnowsky, Mechtilde von, 1912-23, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 203-07)
  - Liebknecht, Sophie [with transcripts]; contract, 1921 Mar; n.d. (Box 6, Folder 208)
  - Lossow, Else (von Hollander-Glawe) von (Box 6, Folder 209)
    Empty folder
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Hollander-Lossow, Else v. Box 5, folder 156a
  - Madelung, Aage, 1917-22 (Box 6, Folder 210)
  - Mahler, Alma, includes contract, 1917-22, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 210a-c)
  - Mann, Heinrich [with transcripts], 1916-17 (Box 6, Folder 211)
  - Mann, Thomas [with transcripts], 1922-36 (Box 6, Folder 212)
  - Masereel, Frans, 1919-35 (Box 6, Folder 213-15)
  - Matthias, Leo, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 216)
  - Mehring, Walter, 1921-22 (Box 6, Folder 217)
  - Meid, Hans, 1921-22 (Box 6, Folder 218)
  - Meidner, Ludwig [with transcripts], 1914-20 (Box 6, Folder 219-20)
  - Meyrink, Gustav
    - Correspondence [with transcripts], 1911-23 (Box 6, Folder 221-24)
    - Der ewige Jude, [1914?] (Box 6, Folder 225)
    - Papers, 1916-24 (Box 6, Folder 226-28)
  - Molo, Walter von, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 229)
  - Mühsam, Erich, 1916-21 (Box 6, Folder 230)
  - Muncker, Franz [with transcript], 1916 Apr 20 (Box 6, Folder 231)
  - Nauen, Heinrich, 1920 Apr 20, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 232)
  - Nexo, Martin Andersen (Box 6, Folder 233)
    See: Andersen Nexo, Martin Box 1, folder 2a
  - Nietzsche, Elisabeth Förster- (Box 6, Folder 234)
    See: Förster-Nietzsche, Elisabeth Box 2, folder 71a
  - Nolde, Emil [with transcripts], 1917-20 (Box 6, Folder 235)
  - Oppenheimer, Max, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 236)
  - Paquet, Alfons, 1919-22, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 237-38)
  - Perzynski, Friedrich [with transcript], 1919-23, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 239-40)
  - Pinder, Wilhelm, 1921-29 (Box 6, Folder 241-42)
  - Polgar, Alfred [with transcript], 1917 (Box 6, Folder 243)
  - Pulver, Max [with transcript], 1917, 1930, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 244)
  - Queri, Georg, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 245)